<hw name="Homework 2" due_date="10/4/2013 17:00:00">

  <question>

    <p>A study of young children found that those with more body fat tended to 
      have more "controlling" mothers; the <i>San Francisco Chronicle</i> 
      concluded that "Parents of Fat Kids Should Lighten Up."</p>

    <ol type="a">

      <li>Was this an observational study or a randomized controlled experiment?
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <options>
	    <option correct="true">observational study</option>
	    <option>randomized controlled experiment</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>

      <li>Did the study find an association between mother's behavior and her 
	child's level of body fat?
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <options>
	    <option correct="true">yes</option>
	    <option>no</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>

      <li>Suppose controlling behavior by the mother causes children to eat 
	more. Would this fact alone explain an association between 
	controlling behavior by the mother and her child's level of body fat?
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <options>
	    <option correct="true">yes</option>
	    <option>no</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>

      <li>Suppose there is a gene which causes obesity. Would this fact alone 
	explain an association between 
	controlling behavior by the mother and her child's level of body fat?
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <options>
	    <option>yes</option>
	    <option correct="true">no</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>
	In a study to test the <i>Chronicle</i>'s conclusion, what would 
be the treatment and control groups?
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <options>
	    <option>overweight and normal weight children</option>
	    <option correct="true">controlling and normal parents</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>

      <li>
	Do the data provide strong support for the <i>Chronicle</i>'s conclusion?
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <options>
	    <option>yes</option>
	    <option correct="true">no</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>
      
    </ol>

  </question>


  <question>
    A scientist is studying the affect of temperature on a certain species of bacteria. 
    To do so, he measures the metabolic rate of different bacteria colonies from this 
    species 20 times over a wide range of different temperatures that he sets in his 
    lab. He then computes the correlation of metabolic rate and temperature for this 
    species and is surprised to find a very small correlation of -0.04, very 
    close to 0. He concludes that temperature has essentially no effect on 
    metabolism for this species. Do you agree with his analysis?
    <item type="Long Answer" points="6">
      <solution>
	<h4>Sample Correct Solution</h4>
	<p>Not necessarily. It's possible to imagine his species of bacteria having an 
	  optimum temperature at which its metabolic rate is highest, so that if you 
	  make the species too hot or too cold, its metabolism decreases. The plot of 
	  metabolism versus temperature would then look roughly like an upside-down U. 
	  The correlation cannot capture this nonlinear association, so the correlation 
	  would be close to 0, even though temperature has a strong effect on 
	  metabolism. A scatterplot, on the other hand, would easily reveal the pattern.</p>
	<h4>Grading Rubric</h4>
	<p>Please grade this question out of 6 points following these guidelines.</p>
	<ul>
          <li>3 points for realizing that the correlation statistic does not fully describe associations between variables</li>
          <li>3 points for suggesting a way that the scientist might have observed a low correlation despite a relatively strong causal relationship</li>
          <li>Feel free to give partial credit or to use your good judgement if you think the case merits it</li>
	</ul>
      </solution>
    </item>
  </question>


  <question>
    <p>People who get lots of vitamins by eating five or more servings of fresh 
      fruit and vegetables each day (especially "cruciferous" vegetables 
      like broccoli) have
      much lower death rates from colon cancer and lung cancer,
      according to many observational studies. These studies were so
      encouraging that two randomized controlled experiments were
      done. The treatment groups were given large doses of vitamins
      supplements, while people in the control groups just ate their
      usual diet. One experiment looked at colon cancer; the other, at
      lung cancer.</p>

    <p>The first experiment found no difference in the death rate from colon
      cancer between the treatment group and the control group. The second
      experiment found that beta carotene (as a diet supplement) increased the
      death rate from lung cancer. True of false, and explain:</p>

    <ol type="a">
      <li>
	The experiments confirmed the results of the observational studies.
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="2">
	  <options>
	    <option>True</option>
	    <option correct="true">False</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>
	The observational studies could easily have reached the wrong
	conclusions, due to confounding -- people who eat lots of
	fruit and vegetables have lifestyles that are different in
	many other ways too.
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="2">
	  <options>
	    <option correct="true">True</option>
	    <option>False</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>
	The experiments could easily have reached the wrong conclusion, due to
	confounding -- people who eat lots of fruit and
	vegetables have lifestyles that are different in many
	other ways too. 
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="2">
	  <options>
	    <option>True</option>
	    <option correct="true">False</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </question>


  <question>
    <p>A longitudinal study of human growth was started in 1929 at the Berkeley 
      Institute of Human Development. The scatter diagram below shows the 
      heights of 64 boys, measured at ages 4 and 18.</p>

    <div align="center"><img src="/class/stats60/img/scatter.png"/></div>

    <ol type="a">
      <li>The average height at age 4 is around 
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <options>
	    <option>38 inches</option>
	    <option correct="true">42 inches</option>
	    <option>44 inches</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>The SD of height at age 18 is around 
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <options>
	    <option>0.5 inches</option>
	    <option>1.0 inches</option>
	    <option correct="true">2.5 inches</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>The correlation coefficient is around 
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="2">
	  <options>
	    <option>-0.98</option>
	    <option>-0.8</option>
	    <option>-0.4</option>
	    <option>0</option>
	    <option>0.4</option>
	    <option correct="true">0.8</option>
	    <option>0.98</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>The two lines are the SD line and the regression line. Which 
	one is the regression line?
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="2">
	  <options>
	    <option>solid</option>
	    <option correct="true">dashed</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </question>
  
  <question>
    <p>
      A study is carried out to determine the effect of party affiliation on
      voting behavior in a certain city. The city is divided up into two wards.
      In each ward, the percentage of registered Democrats who vote is higher
      than the percentage of registered Republicans who vote. True or false:
      For the city as a whole, the percentage of registered Democrats who vote
      must be higher than the percentage of registered Republicans who vote.
      If true, please explain why, and if false, please give a counterexample.
    </p>
    <item type="Long Answer" points="6">
      <solution>
	<h4>Sample Correct Solution</h4>
	<p>
          False: This is exactly Simpson's Paradox. For example, in Ward A
          1000 out of 10000 registered Republicans might vote, and 2000 out of
          10000 registered Democrats. In Ward B, 22000 out of 50000 Republicans
          might vote, and 5000 out of 10000 registered Democrats might vote.
	</p>
	<p>
          Then in Ward A, 10% of Republicans vote and 20% of Democrats vote. In
          Ward B, 44% of Republicans vote and 50% of Democrats vote. But in total,
          (1000 + 22000) / (10000 + 50000) = 38.3% of Republicans vote, but only
          (2000 + 5000) / (10000 + 10000) = 35% of Democrats vote.
	</p>
	<h4>Grading Rubric</h4>
	<p>Please grade this question out of 6 points following these guidelines.</p>
	<ul>
          <li>2 points for getting the conclusion right</li>
          <li>4 points for giving an explicit example of how such a situation might occur.</li>
          <li>Feel free to give partial credit or to use your good judgement if you think the case merits it</li>
	</ul>
      </solution>
    </item>
    
  </question>


  <question>
    <p>A number is missing in each of the data sets below. If possible, fill in the 
      blank to make $r = 1$. If this is not possible, type in "x" into the blank.</p>
    
    <div>
    <table class='table span2'>
      <thead>
	<th>$x$</th>
	<th>$y$</th>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
	<tr><td>1</td><td>1</td></tr>
	<tr><td>2</td><td>3</td></tr>
	<tr><td>2</td><td>3</td></tr>
	<tr><td>4</td>
	  <td>
	    <item type="Short Answer" points="3">
	      <answer type="range">[7,7]</answer>
	    </item>
	  </td>
	</tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
    </div>

    <hr/>
    
    <div>
    <table class='table span2'>
      <thead>
	<th>$x$</th>
	<th>$y$</th>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
	<tr><td>1</td><td>1</td></tr>
	<tr><td>2</td><td>3</td></tr>
	<tr><td>3</td><td>4</td></tr>
	<tr><td>4</td>
	  <td>
	    <item type="Short Answer" points="3">
	      <answer type="exact">x</answer>
	    </item>
	  </td>
	</tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
    </div>
    
  </question>


  <question>
    <p>Breast cancer is one of the most common malignancies among women in 
      Canada and the U.S. If it is detected early enough -- before the 
      cancer spreads -- chances of successful treatment are much better. 
      Do screening programs speed up detection by enough to matter? Many 
      studies have examined this question.</p>
    
    <p>The Canadian National Breast Cancer Study was a randomized controlled 
      experiment on mammography, that is, x-ray screening for breast cancer. 
      The study found no benefit from screening. (The benefit was measured 
      by comparing death rates from breast cancer in the treatment and 
      control groups.)</p>
    
    <p>Dr. Daniel Kopans argued that the randomization was not done properly: 
      instead of following instructions, nurses assigned high risk women to the 
      treatment group.</p> 

    <ol type="a">
      <li>Would this bias the study? If so, would the bias make 
      the benefit from screening look bigger or smaller than it really is? 
      Explain your answer.</li>
      <li>What one change to the study could have ensured a proper randomization?</li>
    </ol>

    <item type="Long Answer" points="6">
      <solution>

	<h4>Sample Correct Solution</h4>

	<p>Moving high-risk women from the control group to the treatment group lowers
	  the death rate in the control group and increases the death rate in the treatment
	  group. That biases the study against screening.</p>

	<p>To ensure proper randomization, the nurses should have been blinded to the 
	  risk status of the patients.</p>

	<h4>Grading Rubric</h4>

	<p>This question is worth 6 points, according to the following guidelines.</p>

	<ul>
	  <li>2 points for realizing that moving high-risk women from control to 
	  treatment biases the study against the treatment.</li>
	  <li>2 points for realizing that this makes the benefit from screening 
	  smaller than it really is.</li>
	  <li>2 points for arguing that the nurses should have been <i>blinded</i> to the 
	  risk status of the patients. (It is important to refer to the term <i>blind</i> 
	  specifically.) Accept other answers that are convincingly argued.</li>
	</ul>

	<p>Partial credit is awarded as appropriate.</p>

      </solution>
    </item>

  </question>


  <question>
    <p>
      A teaching assistant gives a quiz with 10 questions and no part credit.
      After grading the papers, the TA writes down for each student the number
      of questions the student got right and the number wrong. The average number
      of right answers is 6.4 with an SD of 2.0; the average number of wrong
      answers is 3.6 with an SD of 2.0. The correlation between the number of
      right answers and the number of wrong answers is:
    </p>
    <item type="Multiple Choice" points="6">
      <options>
	<option correct="false">0.00</option>
	<option correct="false">-0.20</option>
	<option correct="false">0.20</option>
	<option correct="false">-0.50</option>
	<option correct="false">0.50</option>
	<option correct="true">-1.00</option>
	<option correct="false">1.00</option>
	<option correct="false">Not enough information to tell.</option>
      </options>
    </item>
  </question>
  

  <question>
    <p>An investigator measuring various characteristics of a large group 
      of athletes found that the correlation between the weight of an 
      athlete and the amount of weight that athlete could lift was 0.60. 
      Determine whether each of the following interpretations of the 
      correlation is true or false:</p>

    <ol type="a">
      <li>
	On the average, an athlete can lift 60% of his body weight.
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <options>
	    <option>True</option>
	    <option correct="true">False</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>
	If an athlete gains 10 pounds, he can expect to lift an additional 6 pounds.
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <options>
	    <option>True</option>
	    <option correct="true">False</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>
	60% of an athlete's lifting ability can be attributed to his weight alone.
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <options>
	    <option>True</option>
	    <option correct="true">False</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>
	The more an athlete weighs, on the average the more he can lift.
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <options>
	    <option correct="true">True</option>
	    <option>False</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>
	The more an athlete can lift, on the average the more he weighs.
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <options>
	    <option correct="true">True</option>
	    <option>False</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>
	The positive correlation suggests that an athlete who wants to lift more 
	should try to gain weight.
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <options>
	    <option>True</option>
	    <option correct="true">False</option>
	  </options>
	</item>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </question>


</hw>
