<hw name="Homework 3" due_date="10/11/2013 17:00:00">

  <question>
    <p>In a large statistics class, the correlation between midterm scores 
      and final scores is found to be nearly 0.7, every term. The scatter diagrams 
      are football-shaped. Predict the percentile rank on the final for a student 
      whose percentile rank on the midterm is:</p>
    <ol type="a">
      <li>5%:
        <item type="Short Answer" points="2">
          <answer type="range">[12.4, 12.6]</answer>
          <answer type="exact">12.5</answer>
        </item>%
      </li>
      <li>80%:
        <item type="Short Answer" points="2">
          <answer type="range">[72, 72.7]</answer>
          <answer type="exact">72.2</answer>
        </item>%
      </li>
      <li>50%:
        <item type="Short Answer" points="1">
          <answer type="range">[50, 50]</answer>
          <answer type="exact">50</answer>
        </item>%
      </li>
      <li>unknown:
        <item type="Short Answer" points="1">
          <answer type="range">[50, 50]</answer>
          <answer type="exact">50</answer>
        </item>%
      </li>
    </ol>
  </question>

  <question>
    <p>A basketball coach conducts an interesting experiment to help his players hit three pointers. 
      On Monday, he has each player on his team take ten shots from right behind the three point 
      line, in the middle of the court. If the player makes three or fewer of his shots, then 
      the coach makes him run ten laps around the court. In the player makes seven or more shots, 
      then the coach high-fives him and buys him a Gatorade. Finally, if the player makes between 
      four and six shots, then the coach just tells him &quot;good job&quot;.</p>
    <p>On Tuesday, he has each player take ten shots again from the same location. The coach 
      observes that the players he made run laps on Monday tended to make more shots on Tuesday, the 
      players he rewarded with a Gatorade tended to make fewer shots on Tuesday, and the players 
      to whom he said &quot;good job&quot; made the same number of shots. To verify this hypothesis, 
      the coach repeats this experiment five times, and finds that the same conclusions hold. 
      The coach concludes that praise doesn't work on basketball players, and decides 
      that in his practices when players miss too many shots he will just make them run laps.</p>
    <p>Do you agree with the coach's conclusions?</p>
    <item type="Long Answer" points="6">
      <solution>
        <h4>Sample Correct Solution</h4>
        <p>
          Not necessarily. It's very possible that the coach is just observing regression to the 
	  mean. We would expect the players who did poorly on Monday to improve on Tuesday, and the 
	  people who played well to do worse, regardless of the treatment. 
        </p>
        <h4>Grading Rubric</h4>
        <p>Please grade this question out of 6 points following these guidelines.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>2 points for getting the conclusion right</li>
	  <li>2 points for recognizing "regression to the mean" or "regression effect". The 
	  student need not use these terms explicitly if they understand the idea.</li>
	  <li>2 points for using the regression effect to explain <b>both</b> why the players who 
	  were punished did better <b>and</b> why the players who were rewarded did worse.</li>
          <li>It is a common misconception that if a player did below average on Monday, he'll 
	    do above average on Tuesday. In fact, his average on Tuesday would be no 
	    different from on any other days, it's just that he'll tend to do better than on 
	    Monday because Monday was below average. Take off 2 points if the student makes 
	    this mistake.</li>
          <li>Feel free to give partial credit or to use your good judgement if you think the case merits it</li>
        </ul>
      </solution>
    </item>
  </question>

  <question>
    <p>Pearson and Lee obtained the following results in a study of about 1,000 families.</p>

    \begin{align}
    \text{avg height of husband} &#038;\approx \text{68 in} &#038; SD &#038;\approx \text{2.7 in} \\
    \text{avg height of wife} &#038;\approx \text{63 in} &#038; SD &#038;\approx \text{2.5 in} &#038; r \approx 0.25
    \end{align}

    <ol type="a">
      <li>Predict the height of a husband when the height of his wife is 65 in.
	<item type="Short Answer" points="2">
	  <answer type="range">[68.5, 68.61]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">68.54</answer>
	</item>in
      </li>
      <li>What is the SD of the heights of husbands whose wives are 65 in tall?
	<item type="Short Answer" points="2">
	  <answer type="range">[2.58, 2.63]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">2.61</answer>
	</item>in
      </li>
      <li>Among wives that are 65 in tall, what percentage have husbands who are taller 
	(than 65 in)?
	<item type="Short Answer" points="2">
	  <answer type="range">[91, 92]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">91.2</answer>
	</item>%
      </li>
    </ol>
  </question>

  <question>
    <p>A sociologist wants to model the how someone's self-satisfaction varies with the number of 
      online friends they have. To do so, she recruits 53 facebook users as subjects for a study. 
      She has each subject complete a self-satisfaction questionaire (scored from 1 to 10), and 
      records the number of Facebook friends that person has. She gathers the following 
      (summarized data):</p>
    <p>Facebook friends: mean = 333.7, SD = 255.9</p>
    <p>Self satisfaction: mean = 5.5, SD = 2.7</p>
    <p>Regression line: 
      $$\text{satisfaction} = 2.705 + 0.00842 \times \text{number of Facebook friends}$$
    </p>

    <p>What is the correlation coefficient? (Hint: Remember that that regression line 
      predicts that \(Y\) increases by \(r\) SD's for every 1 SD increase in \(X\).)</p>

    <item type="Short Answer" points="2">
      <answer type="range">[0.79, 0.81]</answer>
      <answer type="exact">0.80</answer>
    </item>

    <p>The sociologist then decides that self statisfaction really ought to be measured from 
      0 to 100. So she takes every self satisfaction score, subtracts 1, and then multiplies it 
      by 100/9. (For example, an initial score of 5 would become 44.44). And she decides that 
      for convenience, it's easier to measure Facebook friends in units of 100. So she divides 
      everyone's friend count by 100. What are the new values for the following quantities?</p>

    <ol type="a">
      <li>new slope:
        <item type="Short Answer" points="2">
          <answer type="range">[9.30, 9.40]</answer>
          <answer type="exact">9.36</answer>
        </item>
      </li>
      <li>new intercept:
        <item type="Short Answer" points="1">
          <answer type="range">[18.7, 18.9]</answer>
          <answer type="exact">18.77</answer>
        </item>
      </li>
      <li>new correlation:
        <item type="Short Answer" points="1">
          <answer type="range">[0.79, 0.81]</answer>
          <answer type="exact">0.80</answer>
        </item>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </question>

  <question>
    <p>Ms. Bubblegum's 4th grade class all had to run a mile today. Everyone in the class 
      recently had a physical, where their leg lengths were measured (in inches), and of 
      course Ms. Bubblegum measured everyone's mile times (in seconds). The average mile 
      time was 450 seconds and the SD of mile times was 30 seconds. 
      The scatterplot of leg lengths and mile times is football-shaped.</p>

    <ol type="a">
      <li>Based on your knowledge about the relationship between leg lengths and mile times, 
which of the following was the correlation?
        <item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
          <options>
	    <option>-1</option>
	    <option correct="true">-.4</option>
	    <option>0</option>
	    <option>.4</option>
	    <option>1</option>
          </options>
        </item>
      </li>
      <li>Using your answer to (a), what mile time would you expect from a 
	student whose leg length is in the 20th percentile?
        <item type="Short Answer" points="2">
          <answer type="range">[460, 460.3]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">460.1</answer>
        </item>
      </li>
      <li>Among students in the 20th percentile, what percentage ran faster than the 
	class average of 450 seconds?
	<item type="Short Answer" points="2">
	  <answer type="range">[63, 66]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">64.3</answer>
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>Consider a student who ran a 420 second mile today. If she were timed again 
	next week, which of the following would be a reasonable percentile for her mile time 
	to fall?
        <item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
          <options>
            <option>10th</option>
            <option correct="true">30th</option>
            <option>50th</option>
            <option>70th</option>
            <option>90th</option>
          </options>
        </item>
      </li>      
    </ol>
  </question>

  <question>
    <p>The average SAT Writing score of incoming Stanford freshmen is approximately 650 with 
    an SD of 50. The average GPA in PWR classes at Stanford is 3.0 with an SD of 0.4. The 
    scatterplot of students' SAT Writing score and PWR GPA is football-shaped with a correlation 
      of 0.50.</p>

    <p>Among students who scored a 750 on the SAT Writing, what percentage will earn at least an 
      A- (GPA > 3.7) in PWR?</p>

    <item type="Short Answer" points="6">
      <answer type="range">[18, 20]</answer>
      <answer type="exact">19.5</answer>
    </item>%
  </question>

  <question name="Sports Illustrated Jinx">
    <p>Athletes who appear on the cover of Sports Illustrated magazine will subsequently 
      perform worse. Is this a jinx?</p>
    
    <p>Let's imagine that we have some way of comparing athletes' performances across 
      sports. Only the best athletes get their photos on the cover of SI, so let's 
      suppose that such athletes are at the 95th percentile among all athletes that week. 
      Also, suppose the correlation of ``performance'' from one week to the next is $0.6$.</p>
    
    <p>What percentage of the athletes on the cover of SI one week (i.e., at the 95th 
      percentile) would you naturally expect to do worse the next (i.e., below the 95th 
      percentile of all players)? Show your work.</p>

    <item type="Long Answer" points="6">
      <solution>
        <h4>Sample Correct Solution</h4>
        <p>
	  Work in standard units. Athletes at the 95th percentile this week have a $z$-score 
	  of 1.65. Since the correlation is 0.6, we would expect them to be at a $z$-score of 
	  $0.6 \times 1.65 = 0.99$ next week. This is the average performance next week 
	  among players in the 95th percentile this week.
	</p>
	<p>
	  We are interested in the percentage of players who will do better than $1.65$ next 
	  week. To calculate this, we also need to know the SD of performances next week 
	  among players in the 95th percentile this week. This is given by:
	  \[ \text{new SD} = \sqrt{1-0.6^2}\times 1 = 0.8 \]
	  Therefore, a performance of 1.65 represents a z-score of 
	  $z = \frac{1.65 - 0.99}{0.8} = 0.825$ next week. Looking at the normal table, 
	  we would expect about 79% of athletes to perform below this level.
	</p>
        <h4>Grading Rubric</h4>
        <p>Please grade this question out of 6 points following these guidelines.</p>
        <ul>
	  <li>2 points for determining that the predicted performance next week among 
	    people in the 95th percentile this week is 0.99 SD's above the mean.</li>
	  <li>2 points for determining that the "new SD" (the SD of values in the vertical 
	    strip) is 0.8 SD's.</li>
	  <li>2 points for calculating that 79% of athletes in the vertical strip will 
	    perform below the 95th percentile next week.</li>
        </ul>
      </solution>
    </item>
    
  </question>

  <question>
    <p>For the following questions, use the plot below.</p>
    <img src="/static/img/hw3_2.jpg" />

    <ol type="a">
      <li>What are plausible values for the standard deviations of x and y, respectively?
        <item type="Multiple Choice" points="2">
          <options>
            <option>1.6, 3.5</option>
            <option correct="true">4.4, 1.9</option>
            <option>2.0, 2.0</option>
            <option>4.2, 3.9</option>
          </options>
        </item>
      </li>
      <li>What is a plausible value for the slope of the SD line?
        <item type="Multiple Choice" points="2">
          <options>
            <option>0.1</option>
            <option correct="true">0.45</option>
            <option>1.2</option>
            <option>1.65</option>
          </options>
        </item>
      </li>
      <li>Given your answer to part (b), what is a plausible value for the 
	regression coefficient?
        <item type="Multiple Choice" points="2">
          <options>
            <option>0.05</option>
            <option correct="true">0.35</option>
            <option>0.7</option>
            <option>1.05</option>
            <option>1.4</option>
            <option>1.85</option>
          </options>
        </item>
      </li>      
    </ol>
  </question>

  <question>
    <p>Suppose the heights of sons and fathers has a correlation of 0.6, and 
      both sons and fathers have an average height of 68 inches. 

      <ol>
	<li>If the 
	  average height of sons of 74-inch fathers is 72 inches, does this mean 
	  that the average height of fathers of 72-inch sons is 74 inches? Explain.</li>
	<li>If the average height of sons of 68-inch fathers is 68 inches, does this mean 
	  that the average height of fathers of 68-inch sons is 68 inches? Explain.</li>
      </ol>
    </p>

    <item type="Long Answer" points="6">
      <solution>
        <h4>Sample Correct Solution</h4>
        <p>No, the average height of fathers of 72-inch sons should not be 74 inches. This is 
	  due to the difference between the regression line fitting heights of sons to heights 
	  of fathers, and the regression line fitting heights of fathers to heights of sons. 
	  In both cases, we expect regression to the mean, and since 72 inches is above the 
	  mean for sons, the average height of fathers of 72-inch sons should be less than 
	  72 (but greater than 68). If the question were about 68-inch fathers whose sons 
	  average 68 inches, then the answer would be yes, since both heights are already 
	  at the mean, so both regression lines intersect that point.</p>
        <h4>Grading Rubric</h4>
        <p>Please grade this question out of 6 points following these guidelines.</p>
        <ul>
	  <li>4 points for concluding "no" in part (a) and explaining that there 
	    is a difference between regressing y on x and regressing x on y, or applying 
	    regression to the mean to answer the question.</li>
	  <li>2 points for concluding "yes" in part (b) and explaining that there is 
	    no regression when x and y are already at the mean (or equivalent).</li>
          <li>Feel free to give partial credit or to use your good judgement if you think the case merits it</li>
        </ul>
      </solution>
    </item>
  </question>

</hw>
