<hw name="Homework 4" due_date="11/19/2013 17:00:00">

  <question>
    <p><strong>For this problem, please enter an exact 
      expression for the answer. For example, 1-(1/3)^2 or 8/9 
      would be acceptable, but not 0.88889. You do not need 
      to simplify expressions.</strong></p> 
    <p>A die is rolled four times. What is the chance that</p>
    <ol type="a">
      <li>all of the rolls show 3 or more spots? 
        <item type="Short Answer" points="2">
          <answer type="expression">(2/3)^4</answer>
        </item>
      </li>
      <li>none of the rolls show 3 or more spots? 
        <item type="Short Answer" points="2">
          <answer type="expression">(1/3)^4</answer>
        </item>
      </li>
      <li>not all of the rolls show 3 or more spots?
        <item type="Short Answer" points="2">
          <answer type="expression">1-(2/3)^4</answer>
        </item>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </question>

  <question>
    <p><strong>For this problem, please enter an exact 
      expression for the answer. For example, 1-(1/3)^2 or 8/9 
      would be acceptable, but not 0.88889. You do not need 
      to simplify expressions.</strong></p> 
    <p>In a certain corporation, there are 300 male 
employees and 100 female employees.  It is known that 
25% of the male employees have advanced degrees and 
40% of the females have advanced degrees. One 
employee is chosen at random.</p>
    <ol type="a">
      <li>What is the chance that the employee has 
	an advanced degree and is female?
        <item type="Short Answer" points="1">
          <answer type="expression">40/400</answer>
        </item>
      </li>
      <li>What is the chance that the employee has 
	an advanced degree or is female?
        <item type="Short Answer" points="1">
          <answer type="expression">175/400</answer>
        </item>
      </li>
      <li>If it is known that the employee selected 
is female, what is the chance that 
the employee has an advanced degree?
        <item type="Short Answer" points="2">
          <answer type="expression">40/100</answer>
        </item>
      </li>
      <li>If it is known that the employee selected 
has an advanced degree, what is the chance that 
the employee is female?
        <item type="Short Answer" points="2">
          <answer type="expression">40/115</answer>
        </item>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </question>

  <question>
    <p>A box contains 2 red marbles and 98 blue ones. Draws
are made at random with replacement. What's the fewest number 
of draws I have to make in order to have better than a 70% 
chance for a red marble to appear at least once?</p>

    <item type="Long Answer" points="6">
    </item>
  </question>

  <question>
    <p><strong>For this problem, please enter an exact 
      expression for the answer. For example, 1-(1/3)^2 or 8/9 
      would be acceptable, but not 0.88889. You do not need 
      to simplify expressions.</strong></p> 
    <p>A coin will be tossed 10 times.</p>
    <ol type="a">
      <li>Without doing any calculations, which chance 
	is greater: that there will be exactly 6 heads total, or that 
	there will be exactly 2 heads among the first 5 
	tosses and exactly 4 heads among the last 5?
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="2">
	  <option correct="true">6 heads total</option>
	  <option>2 heads among first 5 tosses, 4 heads among last 5</option>
	  <option>The chances are the same.</option>
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>What is the chance that there will be exactly 6 heads total?
	<item type="Short Answer" points="2">
	  <answer type="expression">210*(1/2)^10</answer>
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>What is the chance that there will be exactly 2 heads 
	among the first 5 tosses and exactly 4 heads among the last 5?
	<item type="Short Answer" points="2">
	  <answer type="expression">10*5*(1/2)^10</answer>
	</item>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </question>

  <question>
    <p><strong>For this problem, please enter an exact 
      expression for the answer. For example, 1-(1/3)^2 or 8/9 
      would be acceptable, but not 0.88889. You do not need 
      to simplify expressions.</strong></p> 
    <p>At the first full moon of fall quarter, a group of three
      seniors walk to the Main Quad to kiss freshmen. Each senior 
      asks 5 freshmen for permission to kiss.
      There is a 60% chance a freshman wants to be kissed, and a 40% 
      chance the freshman refuses. Assume independence thoughout.</p>
    <ol type="a">
      <li>First consider only one of the three seniors. 
	What are the chances that this senior will kiss 
	at least one freshman?
	<item type="Short Answer" points="3">
	  <answer type="expression">1-(.4)^5</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">.98976</answer>
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>What are the chances that at least one in the group
	of three seniors has to go home without having kissed anybody?
	<item type="Short Answer" points="3">
	  <answer type="expression">1-(.98976)^3</answer>
	</item>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </question>

  <question>
    <p>You are participating in a game show. The host offers you a choice 
      of 3 doors. He has chosen one of the doors at random and placed a 
      brand new Ferrari behind that door. Behind the other two doors are 
      used Cal sweatshirts.</p>

    <p>The game works as follows: you pick a door, but 
      before the host opens it, he opens one of the other two 
      doors to reveal a Cal sweatshirt. He 
      then offers you the opportunity to switch to the remaining 
      door. Should you switch? Or does it not matter?
    </p>

    <item type="Long Answer" points="6">
    </item>
  </question>

  <question>
    <p><strong>For this problem, please enter an exact 
      expression for the answer. For example, 1-(1/3)^2 or 8/9 
      would be acceptable, but not 0.88889. You do not need 
      to simplify expressions.</strong></p> 

    <p>You are writing an 8 page paper. There is a 40% chance you make 
      no errors on a page, a 30% chance you make 1 error, a 20% chance you 
      make 2 errors, and a 10% chance you make 3 or more errors. Assume 
      the numbers of errors on pages are independent.</p>

    <ol type="a">
      <li>What is the chance that you make errors on fewer than 2 pages?
	<item type="Short Answer" points="3">
	  <answer type="expression">8*(.6)^1*(.4)^7 + (.4)^8</answer>
	</item>	
      </li>
      <li>What is the chance you make no more than 1 error on at least 7 of the pages?
	<item type="Short Answer" points="3">
	  <answer type="expression">8*(.7)^7*(.3)^1 + (.7)^8</answer>
	</item>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </question>
  
  <question>
    <p>The ELISA test screens donated blood for the presence of the AIDS
      virus. The test works by detecting antibodies, substances that the 
      body produces when the virus is present, but it makes some mistakes. 
      ELISA was designed so that when a given blood sample
      is in fact contaminated with AIDS, the test gives a positive result 
      (that is, ELISA reports that in its opinion this blood sample has 
      AIDS in it) 99% of the time, whereas when the blood being
      tested is not contaminated with the virus ELISA will announce a 
      negative result 94% of the time. The prevalence of AIDS in the 
      population of people who donate blood is thought to be about 1%.
      Suppose someone comes in, donates blood, and the ELISA test comes 
      out positive. What is the chance that they actually have AIDS?</p>

    <p><strong>You can round your answer to this problem. We are looking 
	for a percentage.</strong></p>

      <item type="Short Answer" points="6">
	<answer type="range">[14, 14.5]</answer>
	<answer type="exact">14.3</answer>
      </item>%
  </question>

  <question>
    <p>A multiple choice exam has 10
      questions. Each question has 4 possible answers, of which one 
      is correct. A student knows the answers to 3 of the questions 
      and answers them correctly. The student guesses the answers 
      to the remaining 7 questions at random.</p>

    <ol type="a">
      <li>What is the chance the student answers exactly 7 of the 10 
	questions correctly?
	<item type="Short Answer" points="3">
	  <answer type="expression">35*(1/4)^4*(3/4)^3</answer>
	  <answer type="range">[.057,.06]</answer>
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>Given that an answer is correct, what is the chance 
	the student was merely guessing the answer?
	<item type="Short Answer" points="3">
	  <answer type="expression">(.7*.25)/(.7*.25+.3*1)</answer>
	  <answer type="range">[.36,.37]</answer>
	</item>
      </li>
    </ol>

  </question>

</hw>
