<hw name="Homework 6" due_date="11/2/2013 17:00:00">

  <question>
    <p>
    One hundred draws are made at random with replacement from a box with
    ninety-nine tickets marked $\fbox{0}$ and one ticket marked $\fbox{1}$. True or false, and explain:
    </p>
    <ol type="a">
      <li>The sum will be around 1, give or take 1 or so.</li>
      <li>There is about a 68% chance that the sum will be in the range 0 to 2.</li>
    </ol>
    <p>
     Now, suppose that instead of drawing 100 draws from this box with replacement, you draw 10,000 times with replacement. True or false, and explain:
    </p>
     <ol type="a">
       <li>The sum will be around 100, give or take 10 or so.</li>
       <li>There is about a 68% chance that the sum will be in the range 90 to 110.</li>
     </ol>
     <item type="Long Answer" points="6">
       <solution>
         <h4>Sample Correct Solution</h4>
         <p>If you draw $n$ times from the box, the SE of the sum is $\sqrt{n} \times \sqrt{\frac{1}{100}\cdot\frac{99}{100}}$. So when you draw 100 times, the SE is 0.995, and when you draw 10,000 times, the SE is 9.95. And of course, the expected value of the sum is $n \cdot 1/100$, so you expect the sum to be 1 and 100 when you draw 100 and 10000 times, respectively.
         </p>
         <p>Thus, (a) is correct for both 100 and 10000 draws, since the quoted ranges are the expected values of the draws plus or minus the SEs.</p>
         <p>(b) is based on the idea of using a normal approximation. When you draw 10,000 times, this normal approximation is reasonable, since the expected number of draws is so large. But when you draw only 100 times, the expected number of draws is too small to use the normal approximation. So for 100 draws, (b) is false, but for 10000 draws, (b) is true.</p>
         <h4>Grading Rubric</h4>
         <p>Please grade this question out of six points. Award one point each for getting each of the four parts correct, and award the remaining two points for correct explainations</p>
       </solution>
     </item>
 </question>

 <question>
   <p>
     There are 50,000 households in a certain city. The average number of persons
     age 16 and over living in each household is known to be 2.38; the SD is 1.87. A
     survey organization plans to take a simple random sample of 400 households,
     and interview all persons age 16 and over living in the sample households.
   </p>
   <p>The total number of interviews will be around
     <item type="Short Answer" points="3">
       <answer type="exact">952</answer>
     </item>
     give or take
     <item type="Short Answer" points="3">
       <answer type="range">[37,37.4]</answer>
       <answer type="exact">37.4</answer>
     </item>
     or so.
   </p>
 </question>

 <question>
   <p>
     A simple random sample of 3,500 people age 18 or over is taken in a large
     town to estimate the percentage of people (age 18 and over in that town) who
     read newspapers. It turns out that 2,487 people in the sample are newspaper
     readers. The population percentage is estimated as 
     $$\frac{2487}{3500} \times 100\% \approx 71\%.$$
   </p>
   <ol type="a">
     <li>By how much is this estimate likely off? 
       <item type="Short Answer" points="1">
         <answer type="range">[0.76,0.77]</answer>
         <answer type="exact">0.767</answer>
       </item>%
     </li>
     <li>$71\% \pm 1.5\%$ is a 
       <item type="Short Answer" points="2">
	 <answer type="range">[94.8, 95.2]</answer>
	 <answer type="exact">95</answer>
       </item>% confidence interval for the percentage of people (aged 18 or over) 
       <item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
         <option correct="true">in the town who read newspapers.</option>
         <option correct="false">in the sample who read newspapers.</option>
       </item>
     </li>
     <li>The pollsters feel that the confidence interval is too wide and decide to conduct another poll of the town. They want to be able to estimate the percentage to within $\pm 1\%$ with 95% confidence. They would need a simple random sample of at least
       <item type="Short Answer" points="2">
         <answer type="range">[7829, 8236]</answer>
         <answer type="exact">8236</answer>
       </item> people to achieve this.
     </li>
   </ol>
 </question>

  <question>

    <p>A group of 50,000 tax forms has an average gross income of \$37,000, with a SD of \$20,000. Furthermore, 20% of the forms have a gross income over \$50,000. A group of 900 forms is chosen at random for audit. To estimate the chance that between 19% and 21% of the forms chosen for audit have gross incomes over \$50,000, a box model is needed.</p>

    <ol type="a">

      <li>Should the number of tickets in the box be 900 or 50,000?
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <option>900</option>
	  <option correct="true">50,000</option>
	</item>
      </li>
	
      <li>Each ticket in the box shows
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <option correct="true">a zero or a one</option>
	  <option>a gross income</option>
	</item>
      </li>

      <li>True or false: the SD of the box is $20,000.
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <option>True</option>
	  <option correct="true">False</option>
	</item>
      </li>

      <li>True or false: the number of draws is 900.
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <option correct="true">True</option>
	  <option>False</option>
	</item>
      </li>

      <li>Find the chance (approximately) that between 19% and 21% of the forms chosen for audit have gross incomes over $50,000.
	<item type="Short Answer" points="1">
	  <answer type="range">[54,55]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">54.67</answer>
	</item>%
      </li>

      <li>With the information given, can you find the chance (approximately) that between 9% and 11% of the forms chosen for audit have gross incomes over $75,000?
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <option>Yes. All information necessary to calculate this has been given.</option>
	  <option>Yes. We can assume that gross incomes follow the normal curve.</option>
	  <option correct="true">No. We could do it if we assumed that gross incomes followed the normal curve, but they most likely do not.</option>
	  <option>No. We cannot calculate it, and the distribution of gross incomes is irrelevant.</option>
	</item>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </question>

  <question>

    <p>The Residential Energy Consumption Survey found in 2001 that 47% of American households had internet access. A market survey organization repeated this study in a certain town with 25,000 households, using a simple random sample of 500 households: 239 of the sample households had internet access.</p>

    <ol type="i">
      <li>The percentage of households in the town with internet access is estimated as 
	<item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	  <answer type="range">[47.5,48]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">47.8</answer>
	</item>%; this estimate is likely to be off by
	<item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	  <answer type="range">[2.1,2.3]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">2.2</answer>
	</item>% or so.
      </li>
      
      <li>If possible, find a 95%-confidence interval for the percentage of all 25,000 households with internet access. Otherwise, enter 0 in each blank.
	[<item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	  <answer type="range">[43.2,43.6]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">43.4</answer>
	</item>%, 
	<item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	  <answer type="range">[52,52.4]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">52.2</answer>
	</item>%]
      </li>
    </ol>

    <p>Of the 500 sample households in the previous exercise, 7 had three or more large-screen TVs.</p>

    <ol type="i">
      <li>The percentage of households in the town with three or more large-screen TVs is estimated as 
	<item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	  <answer type="range">[1.4, 1.4]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">1.4</answer>
	</item>%; this estimate is likely to be off by
	<item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	  <answer type="range">[0.5, 0.55]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">0.5</answer>
	</item>% or so.
      </li>

      <li>If possible, find a 95%-confidence interval for the percentage of all 25,000 households with three or more large-screen TVs. Otherwise enter 0 in each blank.
	[<item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	  <answer type="exact">0</answer>
	</item>%, 
	<item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	  <answer type="exact">0</answer>
	</item>%]
      </li>

    </ol>

    <p>Among the sample households, 121 had no car, 172 had one car, and 207 had two or more cars.</p>

    <ol type="i">
      <li>The percentage of households in the town with one or more cars is estimated as 
	<item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	  <answer type="range">[75.5,79]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">75.8</answer>
	</item>%; this estimate is likely to be off by 
	<item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	  <answer type="range">[1.8,2.0]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">1.9</answer>
	</item>% or so.
      </li>

      <li>If possible, find a 95%-confidence interval for the percentage of all 25,000 households with one or more cars. Otherwise enter 0 in each blank below.
	[<item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	  <answer type="range">[71.9, 72.1]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">71.9</answer>
	</item>%, 
	<item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	  <answer type="range">[79.5, 79.7]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">79.6</answer>
	</item>%]
      </li>
      
    </ol>
  </question>

  <question>
    <p>NAEP (National Assessment of Educational Progress) periodically tests scientific knowledge in U.S. schools. Here is one question on the test, administered to students in grade 12.</p>

    <blockquote>
      The diagram below shows a thermometer. On the diagram, fill in the 
thermometer so that it reads 37.5 degrees Celsius. 
      <img src="http://stats60.stanford.edu/static/img/thermometer.png" class="span4"/></div>
    </blockquote>

    <p>
    Only 64% of the students who were tested could answer this question correctly. 
    The superintendent of education in a certain state cannot believe these data. 
    To check, he takes a simple random sample of 100 high schools in the state, and 
    tests 10 randomly selected students from grade 12 in each school. 661 out of 
    the 1,000 students who take the test, or 66.1%, can do the problem. With the 
    information above, can you put a standard error on the 66.1%? Find the SE, 
    or say why this can't be done.
    </p>

    <item type="Long Answer" points="6">
      <solution>
	<h4>Sample Correct Solution</h4>
	<p>This can't be done with the information given, because it is a cluster sample. That is, the 1,000 students' answers to the question are not independent, since some of them came from the same school and thus are likely to have been educated similarly. The following is not part of the question asked (and thus not worth any points), but is also worth noting. Since the superintendent only sampled students from his state, even if he did somehow obtain a sample of independent students and thus could compute a SE and thus a confidence interval for his estimate, that confidence interval would only apply within his state. Therefore he couldn't really compare it to the (presumably national) figure of 64%.</p>
	<h4>Grading Rubric</h4>
	<p>Please grade this question out of 6 points following these guidelines.</p>
	<ul>
          <li>3 points for saying the SE cannot be computed</li>
          <li>3 points for stating that it is a cluster sample, or explaining why the observations aren't independent</li>
          <li>Feel free to give partial credit or to use your good judgement if you think the case merits it</li>
	</ul>
      </solution>
    </item>
  </question>


  <question>

    <p>100 draws are made at random with replacement from the box
$\fbox{$\fbox{1}\fbox{1}\fbox{2}\fbox{4}$}$. One of the graphs below is the probability histogram for
the average of the draws. Another is the histogram for the numbers drawn.
And the third is the histogram for the contents of the box. Which is which?</p>

    <img src="http://stats60.stanford.edu/static/img/hw6_1.png" class="span8"/>

    <ol type="i">

      <li>
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1.5">
	  <option>probability histogram for the average of the draws</option>
	  <option correct="true">histogram for the numbers drawn</option>
	  <option>histogram for the contents of the box</option>
	</item>
      </li>

      <li>
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1.5">
	  <option correct="true">probability histogram for the average of the draws</option>
	  <option>histogram for the numbers drawn</option>
	  <option>histogram for the contents of the box</option>
	</item>
      </li>

      <li>
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1.5">
	  <option>probability histogram for the average of the draws</option>
	  <option>histogram for the numbers drawn</option>
	  <option correct="true">histogram for the contents of the box</option>
	</item>
      </li>

    </ol>

    <p>Your friend claims to have drawn the probability histogram for the average of 
      25 draws made at random with replacement from the box 
      $\fbox{$\fbox{1}\fbox{2}\fbox{3}\fbox{4}\fbox{5}$}$. The picture is shown below. 
      Does it seem reasonable?

      <img src="http://stats60.stanford.edu/static/img/hw6_2.png" class="span4">

      <item type="Multiple Choice" points="1.5">
	<option>Yes, with 25 draws, the probability histogram will look roughly normal.</option>
	<option>No, 25 draws is not enough for the probability histogram to look normal.</option>
	<option>No, the expected value is incorrect.</option>
	<option correct="true">No, there are too many bins.</option>
      </item>

    </p>

  </question>


  <question>

    <p>A survey research company uses random digit dialing. They have a contract, to estimate the percentage of people watching Spanish-language television in several Southwestern cities. They took a sample of 1,000 in Austin, Texas--which has about 600,000 residents. They are satisfied with the accuracy of the estimates for Austin. Dallas has about twice the population of Austin, but similar demographics. To get about the same accuracy in Dallas as in Austin, how large a sample size should the company use?</p>

    <item type="Multiple Choice" points="3">
      <option>$1000/2 = 500$</option>
      <option>$1000/\sqrt{2} = 707$</option>
      <option correct="true">$1000$</option>
      <option>$\sqrt{2} \times 1000 = 1414$</option>
      <option>$2 \times 1000 = 2000$</option>
    </item>


    <p>The Census Bureau is planning to take a sample amounting to 1/10 of 1% of the population in each state in order to estimate the percentage of the population in that state earning over \$100,000 a year. Other things being equal:</p>

    <item type="Multiple Choice" points="3">
      <option>The accuracy to be expected in California (population 35 million) is about the same as the accuracy to be expected in Nevada (population 2 million).</option>
      <option correct="true">The accuracy to be expected in California is quite a bit higher than in Nevada.</option>
      <option>The accuracy to be expected in California is quite a bit lower than in Nevada.</option>
    </item>

  </question>

  <question>
    <p>It has been said for many years (or even decades) that there is not much dating going on at Stanford. Some time ago the Stanford Daily did a study to find out the truth. Read the article <a href="http://stats60.stanford.edu/static/html/SexOnFarm.html">&quot;Sex on the Farm&quot;</a> by Ben Friedland. The article describes a survey and concludes that there is an active dating scene at Stanford. Does the survey indeed disprove the myth?</p>
    <item type="Long Answer" points="6">
      <solution>
        <h4>Sample Correct Solution</h4>
        <p>The Daily interviewed students who happened to pass by White Plaza. This is a sample of convenience, not a random sample. Therefore, there is selection bias. For example, studious students may not be walking around White Plaza as much, and these students may also date less. There may also be some response bias because students are more likely to exaggerate their romantic life. Because the sample is not representative of the population, this survey does not disprove the myth.</p>
        <h4>Grading Rubric</h4>
        <p>Please grade this question out of six points. Award three points each for pointing out that there could be substantial selection bias and response bias, and for offering plausible guesses for how they would affect the results.</p>
      </solution>
    </item>
  </question>
</hw>
