<hw name="Homework 7" due_date="11/9/2013 17:00:00">  


<question>
  
  <p>
    A laboratory makes 25 repeated measurements on the molecular weight of a
    protein (in "kilo-Daltons"). The average is 119, and the SD is 15. The lab now
    wants to estimate the likely size of certain chance errors. You may assume the
    Gauss model, with no bias. Explain your answers.
  </p>
  
  <ol type="a">
    <li> The chance error in one measurement is about 
      <item type="Short Answer" points="3"> 
	<answer type="range">[15, 15]</answer>
	<answer type="exact">15</answer> 
      </item>
    </li>
    <li> The chance error in the average of the measurements is about 
      <item type="Multiple Choice" points="3"> 
	<option>$\frac{15}{25}$</option> 
	<option correct="true">$\frac{15}{\sqrt{25}}$</option> 
        <option>$15$</option>
        <option>$15\times \sqrt{25}$</option> 
        <option>$15\times 25$</option>  
      </item>
    </li>
  </ol>
</question>


<question> 

  <p> 
    A real estate office wants to make a survey in a certain town, which has 50,000
    households, to determine how far the head of household has to commute to
    work. A simple random sample of 1,000 households is chosen.
  </p>  
  
  <ol type="a"> 
    
    <li>It is found that on average, the heads of the sample
      households commuted 8.7 miles to work; the SD of the distances was 9.0
      miles. (All distances are one-way; if someone isn't working, the commute
      distance is defined to be 0.) If possible, find a 90%-confidence interval for the average 
      commute distance of all heads of households in the town; otherwise, 
      enter 0 in each blank.
      [<item type="Short Answer" points="1">
	<answer type="range">[8.2, 8.25]</answer>
	<answer type="exact">8.23</answer>
      </item>, 
      <item type="Short Answer" points="1">
	<answer type="range">[9.15, 9.2]</answer>
	<answer type="exact">9.17</answer>
      </item>]
    </li>

    <li>The real estate office in fact interviewed all persons age 16 and over in the 
      sample households; there were 2500 such persons. On the average, these 2,500 
      people commuted 7.1 miles to work, and the SD of the distances was 10.2 miles. (Again, 
      if someone isn't working the commute distance is defined to be 0; and all distances are 
      one-way.) If possible, find a 90%-confidence interval for all people  
      age 16 and over in the town. Otherwise, 
      enter 0 in each blank.
      [<item type="Short Answer" points="1">
	<answer type="exact">0</answer>
      </item>, 
      <item type="Short Answer" points="1">
	<answer type="exact">0</answer>
      </item>]
    </li>

    <li>
      In 721 of the sample households, the head of the household commuted by car. If possible, 
      find a 90% confidence interval for the percentage of all households in the town where 
      the head of the household commutes by car. Otherwise, enter 0 in each blank.
      [<item type="Short Answer" points="1">
	<answer type="range">[69.7, 69.8]</answer>
	<answer type="exact">69.76</answer>
      </item>%, 
      <item type="Short Answer" points="1">
	<answer type="range">[74.4, 74.5]</answer>
	<answer type="exact">74.44</answer>
      </item>%]
    </li>

  </ol>

</question>


<question> 

  <p>
    A survey organization takes a simple random sample of 625 households from
    a city of 80,000 households. On the average, there are 2.30 persons per sample
    household, and the SD is 1.75. Say whether each of the following statements
    is true or false. 
  </p>

  <ol type="a">  
    
    <li> The SE for the sample average is 0.07. 
      <item type="Multiple Choice" points="1"> 
	<option correct="true">True</option> 
	<option>False</option> 
      </item> 
    </li> 
    <li>  A 95%-confidence interval for the average household size in the sample
      is 2.16 to 2.44.
      <item type="Multiple Choice" points="1"> 
	<option>True</option> 
	<option correct="true">False</option> 
      </item> 
    </li>
    <li> A 95%-confidence interval for the average household size in the city is
      2.16 to 2.44.
      <item type="Multiple Choice" points="1"> 
	<option correct="true">True</option> 
	<option>False</option> 
      </item> 
    </li> 
    <li> 95% of the households in the city contain between 2.16 and 2.44 persons.
      <item type="Multiple Choice" points="1"> 
	<option>True</option> 
	<option correct="true">False</option> 
      </item> 
    </li>
    <li>The 95%-confidence level is about right because household size follows
      the normal curve
      <item type="Multiple Choice" points="1"> 
	<option>True</option> 
	<option correct="true">False</option> 
      </item> 
    </li>
    <li>The 95%-confidence level is about right because, with 625 draws from
      the box, the probability histogram for the average of the draws follows
      the normal curve.
      <item type="Multiple Choice" points="1"> 
	<option correct="true">True</option> 
	<option>False</option> 
      </item> 
    </li>
  </ol>
</question> 


<question> 

  <p>
    Laser altimeters can measure elevation to within a few inches, without bias,
    and with no trend or pattern to the measurements. The Gauss model holds. 
    As part of an experiment,
    25 readings were made on the elevation of a mountain peak. These averaged
    out to 81,411 inches, and their SD was 30 inches.
  </p>

  <p>
    For each of the following 
    statements, say whether it is true or false, and explain. If the statement 
    is false, change the statement to make it true.
  </p>

  <ol type="a">
    <li> $81,411 \pm 12$ inches is a 95%-confidence interval for the average of the
      25 readings.
    </li>
    <li>About 95% of the readings were in the range $81,411 \pm 12$ inches.
    </li>
    <li> If another 25 readings are made, there is about a 95% chance that their
      average will be in the range $81,411 \pm 12$ inches.
    </li>
  </ol>

  <item type="Long Answer" points="6">

    <solution>
    <p>All 3 statements are false.</p>
    <ol type="a">
      <li> We don't need a confidence interval for the average of the 25 readings; 
	we already know that it's 81,411! This is a 95% confidence interval for the true height 
	of the mountain peak.</li>
      <li> 12 is the SE, the variability in the average of 25 readings. The variability in 
      the readings is the SD, so about 95% of readings should be in the range $81,411 \pm 30$, 
	assuming the measurements follow the normal curve.</li>
      <li> It's true to say that there's a 95% chance that the average of another 25 readings will fall within 2 SE's of 
      the true mean, but 81,411 is not the true mean.</li>
    </ol>

    <p>Award 2 points for each statement: 1 point for a valid explanation and 1 point for 
    correcting the statement. No points for saying "false" without a valid explanation.
    </p>
    </solution>
      
  </item>

</question> 

<question>
  <p>
    A calibration laboratory has been measuring a one-kilogram checkweight by
    the same procedure for several years. They have accumulated several hundred
    measurements, and the SD of these measurements is 18 micrograms. Someone
    now sends in a one-kilogram weight to be calibrated by the same procedure.
    The lab makes 50 measurements on the new weight, which average 78.1 micrograms
    above a kilogram, and their SD is 20 micrograms. 
  </p>
  <p>If possible, find a 90%-confidence interval for the value of this new weight. Otherwise enter 0 
    in both blanks. (You may assume the Gauss model, with no bias.)
    [<item type="Short Answer" points="3"> 
      <answer type="range">[73.88, 73.92]</answer> 
      <answer type="exact">73.9</answer> 
    </item>, 
    <item type="Short Answer" points="3"> 
      <answer type="range">[82.28,82.31]</answer> 
      <answer type="exact">82.3</answer> 
    </item>]
  </p>
</question>


<question> 

  <p>
    A machine makes sticks of butter whose average weight is 4.0 ounces; the SD
    of the weights is 0.05 ounces. There is no trend or pattern in the data. There
    are 4 sticks to a package.
  </p>
  <ol type="a">
    <li> A package weighs 
      <item type="Short Answer" points="2"> 
	<answer type="range">[16, 16]</answer>
	<answer type="exact">16</answer> 
      </item>oz., give or take 
      <item type="Short Answer" points="2">
	<answer type="range">[.1, .1]</answer>
	<answer type="exact">0.1</answer> 
      </item> oz. or so. 
    </li>
    <li> A store buys 100 packages. Estimate the chance that they get 100
      pounds of butter, to within 2 ounces. 
      <item type="Short Answer" points="2"> 
	<answer type="range">[95, 95.45]</answer> 
        <answer type="exact">95</answer>   
      </item>%
    </li>    
  </ol>

</question>


<question>

  <p>You want to estimate the average starting salary of Stanford graduates. You 
    call a random sample of 200 students who graduated in the last two years. 
    After collecting the data, you are about to calculate the 95% confidence interval 
    when suddenly you remember (from Stats 60!) that incomes are skewed to the right, 
    whereas a normal curve is necessary for a 95% confidence interval. 
    Was all your work in vain? Explain.
  </p>

  <item type="Long Answer" points="6">
    <solution>
      <p>No, you're fine. Even if incomes are skewed to the right, when you sample 200 
      students and take the average, the probability histogram of the average 
      approximately follows 
      the normal curve. To be able to construct a confidence interval, 
      you only need the probability histogram to follow the normal curve.
      </p>

      <p>Award points as follows.</p>
      <ul>
	<li>3 points for realizing that the probability histogram is different from the 
	  histogram of the incomes. (The student doesn't have to mention the term "probability 
	histogram" if they clearly understand what's going on.)</li>
	<li>3 points for realizing that the probability histogram will be normal with 
	200 draws, and therefore the confidence interval is valid..</li>
      </ul>
    </solution>
  </item>

</question>


<question> 

  <p>
    An airline does a market research survey on travel patterns. It takes a simple
    random sample of 225 people aged 18 and over in a certain city, and works
    out the 95%-confidence interval for the average distance they travelled on vacations
    in the previous year. This was 488 to 592 miles. Say whether each
    statement below is true or false.
  </p>
  <ol type="a">
    <li> The average of the 225 distances is about 
      <item type="Short Answer" points="2"> 
	<answer type="range">[540, 540]</answer>
	<answer type="exact">540</answer>
      </item> miles.
    </li>
    <li> The SD of the 225 distances is about 
      <item type="Short Answer" points="2"> 
	<answer type="range">[390, 398]</answer>
	<answer type="exact">390</answer>
      </item> miles.
    </li>
    <li> A 95%-confidence interval based on a sample of 450 people will be
      about half as wide as one based on a sample of 225 people.
      <item type="Multiple Choice" points="2"> 
	<option>True</option> 
	<option correct="true">False</option> 
      </item>
    </li>
  </ol>

</question> 


<question>
  
  <p>
    According to the Stanford University Common Data Set 2012-13, 69.46% of Stanford freshmen 
    had an SAT Reading score of at least 700. (The number of freshmen who took the SAT 
    was 1,552.) The Stanford Daily happens to be doing a survey and takes a simple random sample of 100 
    students. 75 of these students report getting an SAT Reading score $\geq 700$.
  </p>

  <p>Answer the following questions, and explain.</p>

  <ol type="a">
    <li>What is the SE (exact, not approximate) of the percentage of Stanford students with an SAT Reading score $\geq 700$ in the sample?</li>
    <li>True or false: There is about a 95% chance that if the Daily were to take another random sample of 100 students that the percentage with a score $\geq 700$ would be in the range $75\% \pm 2\cdot SE$.</li>
    <li>True or false: There is about a 95% chance that if the Daily were to take another random sample of 100 students that the percentage with a score $\geq 700$ would be in the range $69.46\% \pm 2\cdot SE$.</li>
  </ol>

  <item type="Long Answer" points="6">
    <solution>
      <ol>
	<li>The exact SE is $\frac{\sqrt{.6946(1-.6946)}}{\sqrt{100}}$. (Technically, you should also include the correction factor $\sqrt{\frac{1552-100}{1552-1}}$, but this is optional.) We use 69.46% because that is the percentage of 1's in the box. 75% would be the bootstrap estimate, but there's no need to 
	  bootstrap when we know the exact number.</li>
	<li>False. This is the confidence interval, but we can't interpret it in this way. The percentage with a score of at least 700 in the sample will follow the normal curve with EV equal to the average of the box, not 75%.</li>
	<li>True. The Central Limit Theorem tells us that the average of 100 draws will follow the normal curve with EV 69.46% and this SE.</li>
      </ol>

      <p>Award two points per item.</p>

    </solution>
  </item>

</question>

</hw>
