<hw name="Homework 9" due_date="11/23/2013 17:00:00">

  <question>
    <p>
      You are drawing 100 times at random with replacement from a box. Select the correct option below:
    </p>
    <ol type="a">
      <li>To test the null hypothesis that the average of the box is 2, you would use:
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="3">
	  <option correct="true">the one-sample z-test</option>
	  <option>the two-sample z-test</option>
	  <option>the $\chi^2$-test, with a null hypothesis that tells you the contents of the box</option>
	  <option>the $\chi^2$-test for independence</option>
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>To test the null hypothesis that the box is $\fbox{$\fbox{1}\fbox{2}\fbox{3}$}$, you would use:
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="3">
	  <option>the one-sample z-test</option>
	  <option>the two-sample z-test</option>
	  <option correct="true">the $\chi^2$-test, with a null hypothesis that tells you the contents of the box</option>
	  <option>the $\chi^2$-test for independence</option>
	</item>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </question>

  <question>
    <p>
      As part of a study on the selection of grand juries in
      Alameda county, the educational level of grand jurors was
      compared with the county distribution.
    </p>
    <p>
      The data on the percentage of people in the county
      and the number of grand jurors attaining each educational
      level is shown below. Fill in the expected number of
      jurors attaining each educational level if the grand jury
      had been selected as a simple random sample from the
      population. (<b>Note</b>: the expected "number" can and should be a 
      decimal.)
    </p>
    <table class="table span5">
      <thead>
	<th style="width:30%">Educational Level</th>
	<th style="width:20%">County</th>
	<th style="width:20%">Number of jurors</th>
	<th style="width:30%">Expected "number"</th>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
	<tr>
	  <td>Elementary</td>
	  <td>28.4%</td>
	  <td>1</td>
	  <td>
            <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
              <answer type="exact">17.6</answer>
              <answer type="range">[17.4,17.8]</answer>
            </item>
	  </td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td>Secondary</td>
	  <td>48.5%</td>
	  <td>10</td>
	  <td>
            <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
              <answer type="exact">30.1</answer>
              <answer type="range">[29.9,30.3]</answer>
            </item>
	  </td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td>Some college</td>
	  <td>11.9%</td>
	  <td>16</td>
	  <td>
            <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
              <answer type="exact">7.4</answer>
              <answer type="range">[7.2,7.6]</answer>
            </item>
	  </td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td>College degree</td>
	  <td>11.2%</td>
	  <td>35</td>
	  <td>
            <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
              <answer type="exact">6.9</answer>
              <answer type="range">[6.7,7.1]</answer>
            </item>
	  </td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td><b>Total</b></td>
	  <td><b>100.0%</b></td>
	  <td><b>62</b></td>
	  <td></td>
	</tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
    <p>The test statistic is $\chi^2=$
      <item type="Short Answer" points="1"> 
	<answer type="exact">153</answer>
	<answer type="range">[152,154]</answer>
      </item>
      with
      <item type="Short Answer" points="1"> 
	<answer type="exact">3</answer>
      </item> degrees of freedom.
    </p>
    <p>Could a simple random sample from the county show a distribution of education level so different from the county-wide one? Choose one option and explanation.
    </p>
    <item type="Multiple Choice" points="2">
      <option>This is absolutely impossible.</option>
      <option correct="true">This is possible, but fantastically unlikely.</option>
      <option>This is possible but unlikely—the chance is around 1% or so.</option>
      <option>This is quite possible—the chance is around 10% or so.</option>
      <option>This is nearly certain.</option>
    </item>
  </question>

  <question>
    <p>
      Two people are trying to decide whether a die is fair. They roll it 100 times, with the results shown below. One person wants to make a z-test, the other wants to make a $\chi^2$-test. Who is right? Explain briefly. Then, calculate the $P$-value of the respective test. Is the die fair?
    </p>

    <div align="center">
    21 <font size="200%"> ⚀</font>'s    &#160;     15 <font size="200%"> ⚁</font>'s      &#160;    13 <font size="200%"> ⚂</font>'s     &#160;     17 <font size="200%"> ⚃</font>'s     &#160;     19 <font size="200%"> ⚄</font>'s    &#160;     15 <font size="200%"> ⚅</font>'s
    </div>

    \begin{align}
      \text{Average of numbers rolled} \approx 3.43, SD \approx 1.76
    \end{align}

    <item type="Long Answer" points="6">
      <solution>
        <h4>Sample Correct Solution</h4>
	
        <p>A $\chi^2$-test should be conducted, because we are interested in how well the rolls match the box, not just the average. For example, if we rolled ⚂ half the time and ⚃ the other half, we would be suspicious even though the average is exactly 3.5 as expected. Thus, we need to see whether the frequency of every outcome is close to its expected frequency, which is $\frac{100}{6} \approx 16.67\%$. With a $\chi^2$-test, $\chi^2$=2.6 on 5 degrees of freedom, which corresponds to $P \approx 75\%$. This is a good fit, and the die is fair. </p>


        <h4>Grading Rubric</h4>
        <p>Please grade this question out of 6 points following these guidelines.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>2 points for arguing that a $\chi^2$-test should be made, with appropriate justification.</li>
          <li>1 point for calculating $\chi^2 = 2.5$.</li>
	  <li>1 point for using 5 degrees of freedom. </li>
	  <li>1 point for calculating $P \approx 75\%$ using the table.</li>
	  <li>1 point for concluding that the die is fair. (If the student calculated an incorrect $P$-value of less than 5%, award them the 1 point for concluding the die is not fair.)</li>
        </ul>
      </solution>
    </item>
  </question>



  <question>

    <p>The U.S. has bilateral extradition treaties with many countries. (A person charged with a crime in his home country may escape to the U.S.; if he is captured in the U.S., authorities in his home country may request that he be "extradited," that is, turned over for prosecution under their laws.) The Senate attached a special rider to the treaty governing extradition to Northern Ireland: fugitives cannot be returned if they will be discriminated against on the basis of religion. In a leading case, the defense tried to establish discrimination in Northern Ireland's criminal justice system.</p>

    <p>One argument was based on 1991 acquittal rates for persons charged with terrorist offenses. According to a defense expert, these rates were significantly different for Protestants and Catholics. The data are shown below: 8 Protestants out of 15 were acquitted, compared to 27 Catholics out of 65.</p>

    <table class="table span4"> 
      <thead> 
        <th></th> 
        <th>Protestant</th> 
        <th>Catholic</th> 
      </thead> 
      <tbody>
	<tr> 
          <td><b>Acquitted</b></td> 
          <td>8</td> 
          <td>27</td> 
	</tr> 
	<tr> 
          <td><b>Convicted</b></td> 
          <td>7</td> 
          <td>38</td> 
	</tr> 
      </tbody>
    </table> 

    <p>The defense expert calculated $\chi^2 \approx 6.2$ with 1 degree of freedom, and concluded $P \approx 1\%$. He concluded that this was evidence of discrimination. In this problem, we will check his work.</p>

    <p>First, fill in the table with expected counts.</p>

     <table class="table span4"> 
      <thead> 
        <th></th> 
        <th>Protestant</th> 
        <th>Catholic</th> 
      </thead> 
      <tr> 
        <td><b>Acquitted</b></td> 
        <td>
	  <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	    <answer type="range">[6.5,6.6]</answer>
	    <answer type="exact">6.56</answer>
	  </item>
	</td> 
        <td>
	  <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	    <answer type="range">[28.4,28.5]</answer>
	    <answer type="exact">28.44</answer>
	  </item>
	</td> 
      </tr> 

      <tr> 
        <td><b>Convicted</b></td> 
        <td>
	  <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	    <answer type="range">[8.4,8.5]</answer>
	    <answer type="exact">8.44</answer>
	  </item>
	</td> 
        <td>
	  <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	    <answer type="range">[36.5,36.6]</answer>
	    <answer type="exact">36.56</answer>
	  </item>
	</td> 
      </tr> 
    </table> 


    <ol type="a">

      <li>What is the $\chi^2$ statistic?
	<item type="Short Answer" points="1">
	  <answer type="range">[0.68,0.70]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">0.69</answer>
	</item>
      </li>
      
      <li>How many degrees of freedom are associated with this $\chi^2$ statistic? 
	<item type="Short Answer" points="1">
	  <answer type="exact">1</answer>
	</item>
      </li>

      <li>According to the table in the book, the P-value lies between 
	<item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	  <answer type="range">[30,30]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">30</answer>
	</item>% and 
	<item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	  <answer type="range">[50,50]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">50</answer>
	</item>%.
      </li>
      
      <li>What do you conclude?
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="1">
	  <option>The expert's calculations were correct.</option>
	  <option>The expert's calculations were wrong but the conclusion is the same: there is strong evidence of religious discrimination in North Ireland's criminal justice system.</option>
	  <option correct="true">The expert's calculations were wrong, leading him to the wrong conclusion: there is no evidence of discrimination from this data.</option>
	</item>
      </li>

    </ol>
  </question>


  <question>
    <p>
      In employment discrimination cases, courts have held that there is proof
      of discrimination when the percentage of blacks among a firm's employees 
      is lower than the percentage of blacks in the surrounding geographical region,
      provided the difference is "statistically significant" (i.e., P-value less than 5%) 
      by the z-test.
    </p>
    <ol type="a">
      <li>
	What is the biggest flaw with the court's criteria for proof of discrimination?
	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="2"> 
	  <option>The difference may be statistically significant but not practically important</option> 
	  <option correct="true">Data snooping makes P-values hard to interpret</option> 
          <option>The test is based on a sample of convenience</option>
          <option>The test is based on data for the entire population</option> 
	</item>
      </li>
      <li>
	Consider a metropolitan area in which 10% of the people are black
	and 50 firms which hire employees independently by a process which, 
	as far as race is concerned, is equivalent to simple random sampling. 
	The chance that at least one of the 50 firms will be found guilty
	of discrimination is <item type="Short Answer" points="4">
	  <answer type="range">[92, 92.4]</answer>
	  <answer type="exact">92.3</answer>
	</item>%.
      </li>
    </ol>
  </question>


  <question>
    <p>
      Juniors in Redwood City high school are assigned to 2 math teachers at random. A simple random sample of 100 juniors was followed for 5 years. Out of 50 juniors in Mr. Smith’s class, 28% majored in a STEM field, 42% majored in a different field, and 30% did not go to a 4-year college. Out of 50 juniors in Mr. Chang’s class, 42% majored in a STEM field, 28% majored in a different field, and 30% did not go to a 4-year college. We believe the teachers had an influence on the students’ future path.
    </p>

    <p>
      Perform a hypothesis test. Show your calculations, and please use the table in the book to calculate the $P$-value. Be sure to state the null hypothesis. 
    </p>

    <item type="Long Answer" points="6">
      <solution>
	<h4>Sample Correct Solution</h4>

	<p>The null hypothesis is that teacher and career path are independent.</p>

	<p>We perform a $\chi^2$ test. First, we write down our observations into a table.</p>

	<table class="table span4">
	  <thead>
	    <th></th>
	    <th>Mr. Smith</th>
	    <th>Mr. Chang</th>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <tr>
	      <td>STEM</td>
	      <td>14</td>
	      <td>21</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>Different Field</td>
	      <td>21</td>
	      <td>14</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>No 4-year college</td>
	      <td>15</td>
	      <td>15</td>
	    </tr>
	  </tbody>
	</table>

	<p>Under the null hypothesis, we have the following expected counts.</p>

	<table class="table span4">
	  <thead>
	    <th></th>
	    <th>Mr. Smith</th>
	    <th>Mr. Chang</th>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <tr>
	      <td>STEM</td>
	      <td>17.5</td>
	      <td>17.5</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>Different Field</td>
	      <td>17.5</td>
	      <td>17.5</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>No 4-year college</td>
	      <td>15</td>
	      <td>15</td>
	    </tr>
	  </tbody>
	</table>

	<p>Calculating the sum of $\frac{(\text{observed} - \text{expected})^2}{\text{expected}}$, we 
	  obtain a $\chi^2 = 2.80$. Comparing this number with the $\chi^2$ table 
	  with $(2-1)(3-1) = 2$ degrees of freedom, the $P$-value is between 10% and 30%. Therefore, 
	  we cannot conclude that the teacher has any impact on students' future path.</p>

	<h4>Grading Rubric</h4>

	<ul>
	  <li>1 point for stating the null hypothesis correctly.</li>
	  <li>1 point for realizing that the $\chi^2$ test should be used.</li>
	  <li>2 points for calculating $\chi^2 = 2.80$.</li>
	  <li>1 point for using 2 degrees of freedom.</li>
	  <li>1 point for determining the $P$-value to be between 10% and 30% from the table.</li>
	</ul>

      </solution>
    </item>

  </question>

  <question>

    <p>
      The Multiple Risk Factor Intervention Trial tested the effect of an intervention to 
      reduce risk factors for coronary heart disease — among them, serum cholesterol and 
      smoking. The subjects were 12,866 men age 35-57, at high risk for heart disease. 
      6,428 were randomized to the intervention group and 6,438 to the control. The 
      intervention included counseling on diet and smoking. Subjects were followed for a 
      minimum of 6 years.
    </p>

    <p><b>First, we look at serum cholesterol levels.</b></p>

    <ol type="a">
      <li>On entry to the study, the serum cholesterol level of the intervention group averaged 253.8 mg/dl; their SD was 36.4 mg/dl. For the control group, the figures were 253.5 and 36.8. 
	Test whether cholesterol levels were significantly different (2-sided) between the two groups before the intervention.

	<p>$z = $ <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	    <answer type="range">[.46, .47]</answer>
	    <answer type="range">[-.47, -.46]</answer>
	    <answer type="exact">.465</answer>
	    <answer type="exact">-.465</answer>
	  </item>, $P \approx $ <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	    <answer type="range">[63.8, 65.3]</answer>
	    <answer type="exact">64.2</answer>
	  </item>%.
	</p>
      </li>

      <li>After 6 years, the serum cholesterol level of the intervention group averaged 235.5 mg/dl; their SD was 38.3 mg/dl. For the control group, the figures were 240.3 and 39.9. Test 
	whether cholesterol levels were significantly different after the intervention.

	<p>$z = $ <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	    <answer type="range">[6.95, 7.0]</answer>
	    <answer type="range">[-7.0, -6.95]</answer>
	    <answer type="exact">6.96</answer>
	    <answer type="exact">-6.96</answer>
	  </item>, $P \approx $ <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	    <answer type="range">[0, 2e-10]</answer>
	    <answer type="exact">0</answer>
	  </item>%
	</p>

      </li>

      <li>Based on your answers to (a) and (b), what can you conclude?

	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="0.5">
	  <option correct="true">Because the groups had comparable cholesterol levels before the intervention 
and significantly different levels afterwards, the intervention helped.</option>
	  <option>Because the groups were not significantly different either before 
or after the intervention, the intervention had no effect.</option>
	  <option>The randomization of subjects to the two groups was poor with respect to cholesterol level, so it is difficult to conclude 
whether or not the intervention helped.</option>
	</item>

      </li>

    </ol>

    <p><b>Next, we look at smoking.</b></p>

    <ol type="a">
      <li>On entry to the study, 52.3% of the intervention group was smoking, compared to 59.0% of 
	the control group. Test whether the two groups had significantly different  
	(2-sided) incidences of smoking before the intervention.

	<p>$z = $ <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	    <answer type="range">[7.4, 8.4]</answer>
	    <answer type="range">[-8.4, -7.4]</answer>
	    <answer type="exact">7.7</answer>
	    <answer type="exact">-7.7</answer>
	  </item>, $P \approx $ <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	    <answer type="range">[0, 7e-12]</answer>
	    <answer type="exact">0</answer>
	  </item>%.
	</p>
      </li>

      <li>After 6 years, 32.3% of the intervention group was smoking, compared to 45.6% of the control group.
	Test whether the smoking incidences in the two groups were significantly different after the intervention.

	<p>$z = $ <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	    <answer type="range">[14.7, 16.7]</answer>
	    <answer type="range">[-16.7, -14.7]</answer>
	    <answer type="exact">15.6</answer>
	    <answer type="exact">-15.6</answer>
	  </item>, $P \approx $ <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	    <answer type="range">[0, 0]</answer>
	    <answer type="exact">0</answer>
	  </item>%
	</p>

      </li>

      <li>Based on your answers to (a) and (b), what can you conclude?

	<item type="Multiple Choice" points="0.5">
	  <option>Because the groups were not significantly different before the intervention 
and were significantly different afterwards, the intervention reduced cholesterol levels.</option>
	  <option>Because the groups were not significantly different either before 
or after the intervention, the intervention had no effect on cholesterol levels.</option>
	  <option correct="true">The randomization of subjects to the two groups was poor with respect to smoking, so it is difficult to conclude 
whether or not the intervention helped.</option>
	</item>

      </li>

    </ol>


    <p><b>The more interesting question, of course, is whether or not the intervention affected cardiovascular disease (CVD). In the intervention 
group, 112 died of CVD after 6 years, compared to 123 in the control group. Does the intervention have a significant effect (2-sided) on mortality from CVD?</b></p>

    <p>$z = $ <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	<answer type="range">[.69, .72]</answer>
	<answer type="range">[-.72, -.69]</answer>
	<answer type="exact">0.71</answer>
	<answer type="exact">-0.71</answer>
      </item>, $P \approx $ <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	<answer type="range">[47, 49]</answer>
	<answer type="exact">47.7</answer>
      </item>%
    </p>

  </question>


  <question>
    <p>
      An experiment aims to test if right or left‐handedness affect how fast people type? 
      Random samples of students from a typing class are given a typing speed test (words per minute),
      and the results are compared.
    </p>
    <table class="table span4">
      <thead>
	<th>Handedness</th>
	<th>$n$</th>
	<th>Mean</th>
	<th>$SD^+$</th>
      </thead>
      <tr>
	<td>right</td>
	<td>16</td>
	<td>55.8</td>
	<td>5.7</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
	<td>left</td>
	<td>9</td>
	<td>59.3</td>
	<td>4.3</td>
      </tr>
    </table>

    <p>Is there a relationship between handedness and typing speed? We will conduct a 2-sample test. Because 
      sample sizes are small we use a t-test.</p>

    <p>First, estimate the common SD of typing speed. 
      $s = $ <item type="Short Answer" points="1">
	<answer type="range">[5.2, 5.3]</answer>
	<answer type="exact">5.25</answer>
      </item> wpm.
    </p>

    <p>Now calculate the test statistic. 
      $t = $ <item type="Short Answer" points="2">
	<answer type="range">[1.58, 1.62]</answer>
	<answer type="range">[-1.62, -1.58]</answer>
	<answer type="exact">1.61</answer>
	<answer type="exact">-1.61</answer>
      </item> with <item type="Short Answer" points="1">
	<answer type="exact">23</answer>
      </item> degrees of freedom.
    </p>

    <p>According to the table in the book, this corresponds to a $P$-value between 
      <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	<answer type="range">[10, 10]</answer>
      </item>% and <item type="Short Answer" points="0.5">
	<answer type="range">[20, 20]</answer>
      </item>%.
    </p>

    <p>What do you conclude?
      <item type="Multiple Choice" points="1"> 
	<option correct="true">There is no relationship between handedness and typing speed.</option> 
	<option>There is a statistically significant, but practically insignificant relationship 
	  between handedness and typing speed.</option> 
	<option>There is a both statistically and practically significant relationship between handedness 
	  and typing speed.</option>
      </item>
    </p>
  </question>


  <question>
    <p>This question is based on this <a href="http://xkcd.com/882/" target="_blank">comic</a>.</p>

    <ol type="a">
      <li>Explain the main point of the comic. Do the findings give us strong reason to believe there is a link between green jelly beans and acne? If not, what error is being made.</li>
      <li>The newspaper article at the bottom of the comic proclaims "Green jelly beans linked to acne! 95% confidence". What do confidence intervals have to do with the hypothesis test the investigators conducted for green jelly beans?</li>
      <li>Suppose the original $P$-value for jelly beans (as a whole) and acne was 6%. Instead of conducting studies for different colors (or playing minecraft), 
	the scientists reconducted the original study for all jelly beans, but with substantially more subjects. They found that eating jelly beans 
	increases risk of acne by $0.05\%$. This difference was very significant, with a $P$-value of 0.1%. Do we now have cause to be concerned about eating jelly beans?</li>
    </ol>
    
    <item type="Long Answer" points="6">
      <solution>
        <h4>Sample Correct Solution</h4>
        <p>The major issue with the comic is that we are testing multiple hypotheses without accounting for it. 
        With 20 different jelly bean colors, even if none of the jelly beans had any effect on acne, 
        we'd expect one false positive. </p>

	<p>Confidence intervals and hypothesis tests are closely related. Rejecting the null hypothesis that green jelly beans have no effect at the 5% level is the same as saying that a 95% confidence interval for the effect size does not include zero. (See Lecture 25.)</p>

        <p>As for the revised study, although the difference is statistically significant, a difference of 0.05% is practically unimportant. 
        </p>

        <h4>Grading Rubric</h4>
        <p>Please grade this question out of 6 points following these guidelines:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>2 points for pointing out that the original comic was testing multiple hypotheses (a.k.a. data snooping) without adjusting for it.</li>
	  <li>2 points for noting that rejecting the null hypothesis in this case means that a 95% confidence interval for the effect size would not include the null effect.</li>
          <li>2 points for remarking on the difference between statistical and practical significance for the new study.</li>
        </ul>
      </solution>
    </item>
  </question>

</hw>
